<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Request presented to the King of Spayn and the Lordes of the Counsel of the State by the inhabitantes of the Louue Countreyes protesting that they will liue according to the reformation of the Gospell, the xxij. of Iune. 1578.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22108141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22108141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25092</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25092)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Request presented to the King of Spayn and the Lordes of the Counsel of the State by the inhabitantes of the Louue Countreyes protesting that they will liue according to the reformation of the Gospell, the xxij. of Iune. 1578.</title>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprintit be Leighe Mannenby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19837.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestant churches --  Netherlands.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:2"/>
            <p>A REQVEST PRESENTED TO THE KING OF SPAYN AND THE LORDES OF THE COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEL OF THE STATE, By the inhabitantes of the lovve Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, proteſting that they will liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reformation of the Goſpell: the .xxij. of Iune. 1578.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>CHARITAS</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Henry Bynneman</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT EDINBVRGH, Imprintit be Leighe Mannenby. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Collegium Sancti Johannis Evangeliſta in Academia Cantabrigienſi</p>
                  <figDesc>bookplate of Saint John's College, University of Cambridge</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all humilitie and reuerence, the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the lovve Countreys do ſhevv, proteſting that they mind to liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reformation of the Goſpell, that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence fiftie yeares paſt and more, ſome of the ſayde Countreys haue bin ſeuered from the Religion, commonly helde in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church, for many reaſons knovvne to the vvhole vvorlde, as vvell by bookes publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as by the confeſsions of many, vvhiche haue yeelded reaſon of their ſeparation, euen to the death. And albeit they haue curiouſly ſearched all the meanes poſsible to roote them out, yet the more they killed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, the more the number hathe encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in ſuch ſort, that euen in the time of the Duke of Alua, vvho as he hath ſurpaſſed the bloudieſt Tirantes in all manner of crueltie, ſo hathe he ſurmounted himſelfe in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, hauing put to deathe betvveene eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene and nineteene thouſande perſons by the hands of the hangman, hauing alſo driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> avvay an infinite number of honeſt people
<pb facs="tcp:25092:4"/>
louers of their Countrey and common vvealth. And yet ſithence notvvithſtanding, that vvhich hath bin practiſed by Don Loys de Requeſens, ſuch deuices haue bin ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard, as vvere forecaſt for the ouerthrovv of the ſaid Proteſtants, vvho contrarivviſe haue ſhevved the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues more openly than before, euen in vvithdravving themſelues from the obedience and ſubiection of the Pope, to certaine vvhole prouinces: and a farre greater number, leauing their Countrey, and the place vvhere they vvere borne, deſiring ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer all extremitie, going voluntarily into baniſhment out of a countrey ſo muche loued of them that are ſtrangers, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ioyfully the loſſe of their goodes, rather than yeelde themſelues ſubiect to the ſayde Romiſh Religion. Then of the baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Duke of Alua, and other the like, there haue follovved great and dangerous vvarres throughout the lovv Countreys, the traffike greatlie decaied, and the handy craftes tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and made common to ſtrange nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in vvhiche things chieflie conſiſted the principall vvealth of the ſaid Countrey.</p>
            <p>But as the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the councell of Spaine,
<pb facs="tcp:25092:4"/>
ſithence this Countrey vvas ioined to it, hath alvvaies bin vvhollie to make theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces ſubiect to the Spanyarde, as in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vvhere they haue ſet their foote, they goe aboute to make the ſubiects their ſlaues and tributaries, and that the moſt part of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of revvarde and recompence, haue long ſince deuoured in their heartes the goodes and poſſeſsions of the inhabitants of theſe Countreys. The occaſion of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſayd Proteſtants, vnder the ſhadovv of deuotion, hathe ſeemed to them a fitte meane to atchieue their miſerable purpoſe to bring all vnder their gouernement, after they had ouerthrovven one of ſo great a ſide, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping prayſe and commendation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, both of godlineſſe and zeale to the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſeruice of God. So youre highneſſe and my Lordes knovve, hovv the Lord Don Iohn going no vvhit out of the vvay troden by the Spanyards, hath gone about by poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and ſubtilties, to make theſe Countreys ſubiect to this miſerable eſtate of bondage, vvhereto the Duke of Alua vvas not able to atteyne for all his crueltie: and hovve by the vvill of God, that vvhiche many, and namely
<pb facs="tcp:25092:5"/>
the ſaid Proteſtants haue vvel foreſeene, hath bin diſcouered, and made manifeſt to euerye one. Whereto at the beginning there vvas made reſiſtance vvith one accord by all good countreymen, and louers of their common vvealth, Religion being ſet aparte, vntill that the ſaid Don Iohn by placards, letters, vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and people ſuborned being among vs, namely by the Ieſuites and other like, hathe laide ſuch foundation, as hath ſeemed to him fitte to breede and mainteyne a deadly diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſovving mutuall ſuſpitions, and defian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by reaſon of the diuerſitie of Religion, a foundation then very fitte, vvhereon to build couertly a vvhole diſagreement and diuiſion of the Countreys, for of the one part he dyd blovve continually into the eares of Prelates and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of thoſe that make profeſsion of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, that the ſayde Proteſtants had no other intente, but vvhen they ſavv time, to take avvay their goodes, and to lay in vvayte for their liues, that for their defence onely he vvas in armes, and that he vvoulde vvarrante them from ſuche and the like daungers, into vvhich they vvould caſt themſelues headlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,
<pb facs="tcp:25092:5"/>
vnleſſe they openly tooke his part. As to the contrary, he ſavv vvell ynough that the ſayde Proteſtants thought as much, ſith that there vvas no ſpeeche touching the quiet exerciſe of their religion, and that they purpoſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but as ſoone as might be, to make them eftſoones ſubiect to the fire, in ſuche vviſe, that of the victory of the common eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, they could not hope for any other frute, after they had faithfully ſpent their liues and goodes, and all that vvhiche God had lente them for the moſt iuſt defence of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and for the expelling of the coniured e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie, but a nevve beginning of miſhappes, vvhich might cauſe that the ſaid Proteſtants (iudging themſelues not to be more aſſured of their Countreymen, vvith vvhome in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon they ſuſteyned the laboures of the vvarre, than of the enimie) tooke partie apart, in good time regarding their ſuretie, ſith that in the end they ſavv no other remedie to ſaue themſelues. And although ſuch vvicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes haue not altogither fallen out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they haue bin deuiſed, vvhich ought to be attributed to Gods prouidence, vvho hath bin vvatchfull ouer this Countrey, and
<pb facs="tcp:25092:6"/>
ouer the vigilancie and carefulneſſe of oure good ſuperioures, and other of oure good Countreymen, ſo neere they had moſt daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous effectes. For vvhereas vve ſhould all haue bin vnited to mainteyne oure libertie, and to preſerue our priuiledges againſte the tyrannie of ſtraungers, contrarivviſe of this curſed ſeede haue iſſued in many the frutes of colde heartes, eſtraungings, and vvithdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vving of mindes, diuers practiſes, ſecrete aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and intelligences vvith the enimie, and generally ſome falſing their faith, haue openly ſtucke to him, and at the beginning making ſome ſhevve to defende themſelues, haue ſuffered themſelues to be caried avvay by the ſayd perſuaſions, vvhiche is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall frute that Don Iohn hathe euer hoped to gather by his craftie skill and diſsimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And in deede, it is impoſsible, that the heartes and mindes coulde vvell vnite and dravve themſelues togither, as in one body, vvhere the one and the other being full of ſuſpition, thinke that euery one hath him for his companion, vvho either is his declared e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie, or vvhich hideth a ſecret hatred vvhich in time and place muſt be diſcouered to the
<pb facs="tcp:25092:6"/>
ſpoyle of the goodes, and life of his fellovve, there is no truſt, but rather a continuall hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den defiance, that engendreth a hatred, and imprinteth in the heart all other ſortes of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement paſsions. And albeit that ſome ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in dealing in the State and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of matters, as naughtie Chirurgions, vvhich ſound not the bothome of the vvou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but contente themſelues to cure the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the diſeaſed member: So theſe men only aſſay outvvardly to heale the hurt, vvithout diſcouering the roote, to pull avvay altogither that hurte vvhiche vvaſteth vs by little and little, euen to our vtter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Notvvithſtanding theſe meanes can not cloſe vp the vvounde of our harmes, but rather it commeth to paſſe that of the one ſide and the other, the leaſt faulte that is committed, is, that the ſeruice of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvealth is ſlovvly and litherly done, and dayly this heate of reſiſting the enimie gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth cold, and it is to be feared, that the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, vvho all this vvhile is not aſleepe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continually ſpreading among vs flames of ſuſpition, vvill in the ende lighten ſuche a fire of diuiſion, that of the one ſide and the
<pb facs="tcp:25092:7"/>
other, vve ſhall be conſumed and deſtroyed by the ſame fire, vvhich our ovvne ſuſpitions and paſsions haue nouriſhed and maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Theſe things haue cauſed that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes, hauing an vnſpeakeable griefe that the Religion vvhereof they make profeſsion, in the vvhich vvithout offending any perſon, they ſeeke nothing but to ſerue God vvith cleanneſſe of heart, is ſo vntovvardly expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that to their greateſt diſpleaſure, they ſee, that it ſerueth Don Iohn for a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhereon to build his practiſes, (vvhich are to oppreſſe the one by the other) as good Countreymen and Citizens they haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſought out the vvelſpring and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of theſe miſchiefes, and if they vvere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, it ſhoulde be eaſie to come to a good vnitie, all ſuſpitions being layde apart, and defiances extinguiſhed, a thing ſo greately deſired of good men, and ſo neceſſarie to the vvhole common vveale. This it is, that of the one part they ſee in many places the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons, to bee in continuall feare, that one daye the ſayde Proteſtantes vvill ſette vppon them, to the
<pb facs="tcp:25092:7"/>
vvhole ouerthrovve of their Religion, and ſpoyle of goodes. Of the other parte, the ſayde Proteſtantes thinke, that they are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reſerued to bee ledde by them to the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, ſeeing that after ſo many loyall ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they can not haue the libertie of their Religion graunted them: vvherevppon there ariſeth ſome proude ſpeeche of both ſydes, and ouermuche libertie of the Souldyoures or people, vvhiche notvvithſtanding, vnder moſt humble correction of youre highneſſe and my Lordes, mighte ſeeme to bee reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, if in dealing vvith both parts freelie, &amp; vvithoute diſsimulation, in diſcloſing among themſelues the cauſes of the miſchiefe, vvhich is but too muche encreaſed, they vvoulde graunte of the one parte the ſayde Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes, the free exerciſe of theyr Religion, ſeeing that this is the onely cauſe vvhiche bringeth them in ſuſpition, and cauſeth that ſome doe enterpriſe matters not pleaſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man. Of the other parte, that the ſayde Proteſtantes by meete meanes, ſhoulde aſſure the ſayde of the Romiſhe Religion, that they ſoughte nothyng leſſe, than to roote oute by force
<pb facs="tcp:25092:8"/>
the ſaid Religion, to take avvay, and poſſeſſe their goodes, and to do any acte contrary to the dutie of their fellovv countreyman. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarivviſe, that they are readye to employe themſelues for the vvhole preſeruation of the Countrey, and of all the inhabitants thereof, as vvel generally, as perticularly: And if theſe things be executed, there is no doubte, but that all matter of diuiſion vvill ceaſſe, and a good peace ſhall be vvell eſtabliſhed, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of mutuall defiance beeyng by thys meane taken avvay, and the old grudges and hatreds altogither buried.</p>
            <p>Moſt humblie beſeeche youre highneſſe, and my Lords, to conſider the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time that they haue looked, that the generall Eſtates ſhould prouide for matters of Religion. But if for the diſcommoditie of the time, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be not yet offered to aſſemble, or elſe by the drift of ſome, vvho fauouring priuily the partie of Don Iohn, do let it, maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by this meane the ſaid defiances, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, vvhiche hope yet after the victorie, to burne the ſaid Proteſtants (meanes no leſſe daungerous the one than the other, and no leſſe vnvvorthy of good Countreymen.) If
<pb facs="tcp:25092:8"/>
then, for ſuche reaſons or the like, they could not yet vvell prouide for this, it reſteth only, (if by your moſt vviſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell there be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedie) the one of theſe tvvo meanes, to vveete, either that the ſaide Proteſtantes, vvho for ſome danger could not be brought to the exerciſe of the Romiſh Religion, doe abide alvvayes vvithout Religion, or elſe that in deede they take in hande the publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion. The firſte is ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the common vvealthe, that nothing can be thought more, for it bringeth vvith it the contempt of God, deſpiſing of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Atheiſme, vvhereof follovveth the breaking of the lavves of God and Man. The ſecond may be a cauſe of a diuiſion in the contrarie, vvhiche mighte turne vpſide dovvne the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente ſtate, the one taking one partie, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther another, vvhich might open a gappe, to ouerthrovv the one by the other, follovving the entrepriſe of the dead Eſcouedo, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie firebrand of this Countrey. But if the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and leſſons of the auntients, and of thoſe vvhich haue bin reputed for their vviſedome, ought to take place, it is certaine, that in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of ſuch vveight, vve can not take better
<pb facs="tcp:25092:9"/>
councell, than of oure enimie: for if this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the diuerſitie of Religion be the beſt vveapon vvhiche he taketh in hande to beate vs, it is good for vs to ſette oure ſide in order, that this falling out, ſerue not him for a breach, to make his tirannie enter in among vs. And for aſmuche as experience of time paſt ſhevveth vs that oure ſinnes haue bin ſo great, that vve coulde not all be broughte to one Religion alone, it reſted (vnder moſte humble correction) to aduice hovv vvithout altering the vnitie of the Countrey, the one and the other Religion mighte be maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vvithoute the preiudice of one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon the ſaide Proteſtantes moſt humblie beſeeche youre highneſſe, and my Lordes, not to giue eare to thoſe, vvhiche to hinder ſo good a matter, alleage firſte of all the pacification of Gant, ſecondly, that tvvo Religions can not abide togither in one Countrey, and thirdly, that there is no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, this point being agreed vpon, that the Eccleſiaſticall perſons may be mainteyned. For touching the firſt, it is vvel knovven, that the enimie hathe plainely renounced it, by
<pb facs="tcp:25092:9"/>
open declaration ſent by Sieur de Selles, that he vvould not in anie vviſe holde it, vvherein he ſhevveth manifeſtlie vvhereat he ſhooteth, and teacheth the ſaid Proteſtantes vvhereof they ſhoulde take heede. Wherefore vve are not bound to keepe oure oth vvith him, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that diſloyally he firſt brake it. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that vvhich toucheth vs among oure ſelues, for ſo muche as the ſaide pacification vvas concluded by the aduice, and conſente of other prouinces, vvith my Lorde the Prince of Orange, and the Eſtates of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Zelande, it is certaine, and nature teacheth it, vvithoute vvronging of any, that there is nothing ſo naturall, but as by the conſent of the tvvo partes, the contracte hathe bin made, paſſed, and promiſed: ſo by the conſente of the one parte and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it could not bee in parte broken, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifyed, and interpreted for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vveale of the Countrey, and for cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the ſecrete vvorking of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie. But the ſayde Proteſtantes thinke not in anye vviſe to vvithſtande it, nor doe mynde to be the cauſe of the breache thereof, ſeeyng that they, abyding in
<pb facs="tcp:25092:10"/>
the tearmes of the ſaide pacification, moſt humblie demaunde and require, that by the meane of the generall eſtates, there ſhoulde prouiſion be made for the free and publike exerciſe of Religion. Concerning the ſecond poynte, experience hath at all times ſhevved the contrary, vvhether vve conſider the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient or nevv Emperoures, or behold the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s neere adioyning. For it is vvell knovven to them vvhich are but meanely ſeene in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, that the Emperoures being at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning Paynims, haue neuertheleſſe mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned vnder their Empire Chriſtians and Paynims, hauing vvhole legio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the reſt of their armie Paynims, all mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vnder one generall of the armie. And notvvithſtanding there vvere founde in that time, as at this preſent, vncircumſpect coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers, vvhiche did put ſuche opinions into their Princes heads, that the tvvo Religions coulde not endure togither, vppon occaſion vvhereof, the Emperoures fell to perſecute the moſt part, but incontinentlie they firſte ſuffered the puniſhmente for ſuche fooliſhe councels. Aftervvard in the times of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Emperours, the like hath bin a verie long
<pb facs="tcp:25092:10"/>
time, and not only that, but alſo amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them that did beare in common the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, the Church hath bin allovved to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d open to them, vvhich helde doctrine altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrarie, vvhiche may be ſeene in the hiſtories of Conſtantine his children Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius and others. As for our time, there are ſo many examples, that if vve are to iudge them by the number, one may ſooner ſaye, and more certainely, that vvhoſoeuer hathe gone about to aboliſhe one of the tvvo Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, hath put his ſtate in greate daunger. Hovvſoeuer it be, if vve looke about vs, the tvvo mightieſt nations, and vvith vvhich vve are enuironed, to vveete, Germanie, and Fraunce, after ſo much ſpilling of bloud, haue founde no meane to ſtaunch it, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to the exerciſe of the one, and the other Religion. We beare yet in minde the greate inuaſions that the Emperoure Charles of moſt famous memorie made into Germanie, of the great likelyhoodes of good ſucceſſe that he had in the beginning, hauing ſubdued the better part thereof, and hauing in his povver the chiefeſt, braueſt, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Princes, the iſſue notvvithſtanding vvas ſuch, that after he vvas brought to greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie,
<pb facs="tcp:25092:11"/>
tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer ſuch a mightie Prince vvas, he had no vvay to aſſure himſelfe, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to the one and other Religion: your highnes grandfather, a Prince of greate and rare iudgement and councell, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Ferdinand perceiuing that he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane to aſſure the one and the other, &amp; to take avvay the ſuſpitions that vvere in Germanie, condeſcended to the Religions-friedt, and ſince that time, there hath not bin one mutinie in Germanie, the Eccleſiaſticall perſons might enioy their goodes, dignities, and preheminences vvith greater aſſurance, than in any other place of Chriſtendome, &amp; in many tovvnes, as at Francfort, VVormes, Vlme, Ausbourg, and others, is exerciſed the one &amp; the other Religion, vvithout diuiſion or vprore in the Churches of any of theſe tovvnes. The Emperour of moſt noble me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie your highneſſe father, hath not onely mainteined that vvhiche hath bin ſo vvell fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by his predeceſſors; but beſides hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved it in his ovvne countreys, vvell percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that this vvas the onely meane to keepe his ſubiects in peace. In like maner, Rodolph your highnes brother, at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t enioying the ſacred ſeate of his predeceſſors, hath not
<pb facs="tcp:25092:11"/>
many days paſt gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ſame to the nobles of his kingdome of Hungarie. I vvill not ſay vvhat the ſtate of Hungarie hath bin ſince Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmund. As touching Fraunce, vve are too neere neybors to be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the ſtremes of bloud vvhich ran in ſuch abundance, could neuer be ſtayd, vntill that ſhe had hir libertie gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, vvhiche hath alvvays brought vvith it quietnes, as vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe vvas hindred, forthvvith the Realme hath bin vvholly on fire, ready to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume himſelf, &amp; to bring himſelfe to aſhes. But if likevviſe vve can take example by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon enimie of Chriſtendome, to vveete, the Turke, vvho knovveth too vvell vvhat it is to beare rule, vve ſee that he ſuffreth alike vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Empire, the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and the Ievvs, being for al this in no doubt of any reuolting, yet he hath vnder his Empire vvithout co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, moe Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vvhich do not acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, nor vvil acknovvlege the Pope, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther be in this Europe, vvhiche do acknovvledge him. The K. of Marroques &amp; Fleez doth the like. And as for the K. of Poland, beſides the diuerſitie of Chriſtian Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he hath in his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, he hath alſo a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometanes, vvhich obey him, not hauing for this reſpect any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. The
<pb facs="tcp:25092:12"/>
Pope himſelfe, vvhome they of the Romiſh Church hold for their head, &amp; his examples for infallible rules, ſuffereth at Rome, and in all places vvhere he hath any propertie, that the Ievves haue their publike Sinagoges, yea for a little money, he vvill ſuffer that euery one may haue it to himſelf. The like is ſeene in many Cities of the Empire. Likevviſe my Lordes, the Eſtates heere vvith vs, haue not let the ſaid Ievves to dreſſe their Sinagogs in ſome places of theſe Countreys, and that in conſideration of a ſmall profite, vvhich in no vviſe is to be compared to that, vvhereof there is queſtion at this preſente. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding, the ſaid Ievves do denie Ieſus Chriſte, and are enimies of the Churche of God, the vvhiche ſhall not be found in thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, vvhich hope in Chriſt, as the onely vvorker of their ſaluation, and are not enimies of the Church, but rather deſire only the reformation.</p>
            <p>As touching the thirde pointe, the ſayde Proteſtants can not ſo ſoone make knovven to al the vvorld, the good deſire they haue to liue peaceably vvith their tovvneſmates and Countreymen, but hope in time to make moſt certaine proofe thereof, the ſaid defian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:25092:12"/>
being ſet aſide, and ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s taken avvay, the vvhich they ſhall promiſe before God to performe. In the meane ſeaſon, they moſt humblie beſeeche youre highneſſe, and my Lords, to offer all ſuch meanes of aſſurance, as you ſhall thinke meete, and they ſhall be very forvvard as muche as lieth in them tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly to obey, and to frame themſelues thereto, and perſuade themſelues vvith this, that they ſhall promiſe, that they vvill finde ſome Princes, good friendes to this Countrey, and great Lords, vvhich vvill doe them this honoure, to aunſvvere for their faithfulnes and ſtedfaſtnes in their promiſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered,<note place="margin">☜</note> the ſaide Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes beſeeche vvith all their moſt humble and obedient heart &amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it vvould pleaſe your highneſſe, and you my Lords, as thoſe to vvhome this common vvealth his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and for vvhich you are bound to giue accompt before God &amp; Man, that it vvould pleaſe you, in taking avvay all occaſions of defiances, and ſuſpitions among the poore ſubiects of the lovv Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, all vvhich bend their eyes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, to find the meanes vvith the liking, and contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all, to agree to the equall exerciſe of both Religions, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:25092:13"/>
that it hath pleaſed God, ſurmounting by his mercy the multitude of our ſinnes (vvhich are the only cauſes of ſo many miſchiefes) by the meane of a good, holy, and free councell ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or at the leaſt nationall, to end the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies that vve ſee in this Countrey, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching matters of Religion, to preuente by your vviſe councels and deliberations, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes as you haue ſeene to light vpon neybours, vvho vvith much adoe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet fetch breath, to cut off by your vviſedome the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes of the enimie, vvho vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovv of this variance, vvould caſt vs headlong into a bottomleſſe pit of confuſion, and by your ripe deliberations, to giue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all the poore ſubiects vvhich feele the ſmart, but looke for the remedie at their handes, vvhome they haue choſen for their Phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and to be guided to the hauen by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhom they haue choſen for their gouernoures. That it vvoulde pleaſe you to behold rather the examples of our neybours and others, of vvhich the one by their vviſe foreſighte haue remedied the miſchiefe to come, the other being taughte by their calamitie, had rather ſeeke remedie, though the diſeaſe hath bin long and deepe rooted, than in deſpairing
<pb facs="tcp:25092:13"/>
their ovvne ſafetie, to caſt themſelues head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into vtter deſtruction. That it vvoulde pleaſe you to haue pitie &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue placed themſelues betvveene your armes, &amp; looke not for any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort next after God, but of you, and ſo doing, ordeine, that by a ſacred lavv of forgetfulnes, al things paſt of the one parte may be buried, vvithout that heereafter none may be ſifted for any thyng happened by reaſon of the diuerſitie of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and the ſaid Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhall promiſe to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to all reaſonable conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſuch as it ſhall pleaſe your highneſſe to offer, to keepe them inuiolably, and to put in ſuch aſſurance, as they are able. And albeit the ſaid Proteſtants ovve themſelues, their liues, and their goods to their Countrey, notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they moſt humblie beſeech, that it vvould pleaſe you to remember, hovve many yeares they haue ſuffered, for the ſeruice of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, and ſince the vnitie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, vvhat their faithfulneſſe &amp; obedience is &amp; hath bin: but if any of them hathe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any acte, vvhich is not allovved of all, there is nothing vvhereto a fitte remedy may not be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and they are not deadly faultes as theirs are, vvhiche openly vnder pretence
<pb facs="tcp:25092:14"/>
of zeale dravve themſelues to the enimie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though alſo that the ſaid Proteſtants ſhould receiue any vvrong vvhiche they hope not, they haue determined by Gods grace, to ſtick to that vvhich they knovv they ovve of duty to their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey. Notvvithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they truſting to your vviſedome &amp; equitie, moſt humblie deſire you to fulfill their requeſt, as for a free recompence of ſo many trauels, and for to encourage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more and more to do vvel, ſo ſhall you do vvell, and the ſaid ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants ſhall be bounde to pray to God for the vvealth &amp; aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your eſtate, the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal &amp; quietneſſe of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, and as til this preſent, they haue bin very forvvard, and diſpoſed to ſerue faithfully, and by the grace of God, vvithoute reproche to the common vvealth, ſo ſhal they ſettle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by means thereof, to do better in time to come.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>OF late aduertiſements are come ouer, that the .xiiij. of this preſent moneth of Iuly, the Eſtates aſſemble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to deliberate vpon this requeſt, the ſequele wherof is vncertaine, for as <hi>Euripides</hi> in <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, Gods doings fall out otherwiſe than men looke for, and he ſaueth whome he loueth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25092:14"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
